This year we learned that you can take
human brains both postmortem and
lab-grown and put them into a robot and
that robot is capable of learning new
skills. Many have expressed the same
concern, which is a great deal. Where
are the ethics when it comes to this?
And I would like to explain that to you
and some of the implications. In 2022,
Cortical Labs, an Australian company,
shocked the world when they claimed
sentience in their lab-grown brains who
played Pong. And just in case anyone is
unfamiliar, you can take skin cells,
turn them into stem cells using chemical
processes, and turn that into a tiny
version of a human brain, a brain
organoid. These are largely used as a
medical platform, although they've also
been used for computation. We saw the
birth of the first data centers that run
on brain organoids. They're not useful
in the same way as a large language
model, although they can run robots and
they're much better at spatial
recognition. Although, you know, you
have to feed them and give them
antibiotics and they're quite fragile.
They are capable of learning in the
period of time that they are alive. And
a short lifespan was one of the limiting
factors, although they now can be kept
alive for 5 years or more and they can
be given a circulatory system or a
little mini spinal cord organoid. They
can also be connected to other organoids
or lobbed together like Legos. This year
though, it was demonstrated that they're
capable of goal-directed learning and
that's what they were trying to
demonstrate as far as sentience goes in
Pong. They're capable of having some
kind of a desire. However, it has
largely been considered irresponsible to
call them sentient or conscious for a
variety of reasons. One of them is that
it just scares people. But also because
both sentience and consciousness are
really not scientific questions because
you can't really demonstrate it.
Researchers have tried for decades to
try to figure out how you can
demonstrate the consciousness exists.
And as AI passes each goalpost, we have
to move said goalpost. And we can all
just agree that we can't answer the
question. It all comes down to I think,
therefore I am. You can only know your
own internal experience. You can't
demonstrate that somebody else is having
one. Unfortunately, I do not think that
our ability to determine if something is
conscious will get better with improved
tools. I mean, yeah, you can kind of
demonstrate that a coma patient is
conscious and it is very concerning as
our little brain organoids start to show
more complex brain waves, but I really
don't think anyone is going to accept
that they are conscious. However, this
question gets significantly more
concerning as researchers from
California actually kept a brain alive
postmortem. Yeah, 24 hours within
somebody's expiration, they removed the
brain, replaced circulation, and gave it
a robotic body of sorts. Yes, that
machine keeps it alive. It has
artificial kidneys, an artificial heart,
and artificial lungs. And yes, that tub,
that vat contains a brain. You know,
brain in a vat was just supposed to be a
philosophical question. I mean, how can
you know if you're really experiencing
the world? You are, you know, in your
head. You have an interface like your
eyes and your skin to feel the world.
But now it's become significantly more
literal.
This is where I provide my disclaimer
because yes, it is metabolically alive.
They did restore circulation and restore
a little bit of cell activity, but it is
not conscious. It is not thinking. It is
essentially a comatose brain that is
barely functional. For now.
I would say that these guys were far
more responsible than our French group
because this brain is not doing
anything. It's not learning anything.
It's also heavily sedated just in case
there is any possibility of
consciousness. But our French scientists
decided to take it in many steps further
and allow it to learn things. Yeah, the
one where they took a postmortem human
cortex slice just hours after
expiration, put it in an incubator,
connected it to a robot arm, and taught
it how to play the piano, and gave it
sensory feedback, and allowed it to
learn new songs.
There is no information in the paper as
to whether or not the original brain
knew how to play the piano, but now it
does. A man asks a surgeon whether or
not he'll be able to play the piano. The
surgeon says, "Yes, of course." And the
man says, "Well, that's great. I
couldn't play the piano before."
I actually spent many years learning to
play the piano, and I have always been
terrible at it. So, this is probably the
only way that I'll ever be able to learn
to play the piano. This technology is
roughly a year old, and the idea of
reviving a human brain was really never
considered to be reasonable. No one
thought it could be done. There has,
however, been a good deal of ethical
research done for brain organoids, and
everyone's kind of come to the same
conclusion. You cannot claim suffering.
You cannot claim sentience in a tiny
brain because we simply do not have
evidence for it. Although, I do like to
tell people that a lack of evidence is
not evidence in itself. Essentially, we
cannot know. So, we should
[clears throat] try to treat them
relatively kindly.
In other words, try to limit undue
suffering. This is one of the reasons
that pain research in brain organoids
bothers me because we are specifically
causing them physical suffering in order
to research them.
One principle in ethics of research is
that you should try to minimize harm.
And if you must cause harm, that should
be balanced with the amount of good that
can come out of it. When it comes to
brain organoids, there's an enormous
amount of good that they can do.
In animal models, they've been an
enormously helpful tool for treating
things like strokes and even
Parkinson's. They're also a great
research model. We can finally research
conditions that we never had any way to
do otherwise, and they represent a very
young brain.
This is the same reason why we're kind
of doing necromancy with brains. It
creates an adult model because when we
are looking at brain organoids, they're
essentially applicable to the age that
they are at. If you keep them alive for
5 years, they have the same protein
expression and gene expression as a
5-year-old child.
But, adult brains have already
experienced a life. They may already
have those neurodegenerative conditions,
and that allows you to study them.
At the same time, we do have a great
responsibility to make sure we are not
accidentally causing suffering. Now,
this stuff really has not hit the news.
The preprint that I showed you from
France was published literally 2 days
ago. Essentially, the public has not had
time to be very concerned about the
ethic yet, and it's also very difficult
to demonstrate any suffering happened.
I mean, how? How would we do that?
Unless the brain slice starts tapping
out help me in Morse code on the piano.
It is just a small piece of brain, and I
feel the same need to do that, to walk
it back, to try to minimize it because I
don't want people to start running with
things that we cannot demonstrate. At
the same time, that is a difficult
balance to strike, because we really
don't know.
What does interest me, and perhaps
morbidly, is what about a collaboration?
Because Bexon does not seem to want to
take their brain in a vat off of
sedatives right now, but we have
demonstrated that adult postmortem brain
could learn new skills. What if we did a
whole brain? What could we do then? What
if we repaired that brain with brain
organoid technology and stem cell
technology? What if we could bring it
back in a robot? That would sound
absolutely insane 10 years ago, and
perhaps it still does now, but I'm
starting to see the possibilities. What
if this technology progresses beyond
where it is right now?
So, to answer the question of how this
passed, well, we don't really have many
protections on brains. They're pretty
much considered other organs. You can
treat them roughly the same way that you
would any other organ in a scientific
study. It also has an enormous potential
to do good.
I hope that helps. I will absolutely
keep you up-to-date, because I am
fascinated by this, too. Follow for
more.